A Guide to the Donald D. Van Slyke papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA203
Rockefeller Archive Center
Donald D. Van Slyke papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Van Slyke, Donald D. (Donald Dexter)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA203
10 Cubic Feet 10 boxes, 4 packages. Volume is approximate
Scope and Contents note
Biography; bibliography; photographs; administrative correspondence.
Biographical/Historical note
Donald Dexter Van Slyke, 1883-1971, biological chemist at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research from 1907 to 1948 when he became Emeritus and worked at Brookhaven National Laboratory until his death in 1971.
His work was chiefly in the chemistry of proteins and protein derivatives and their role in physiology, pathology, enzyme action, blood chemistry and the metabolic conditions of diabetes and nephritis. Co-author with Peters of 2 volumes "Qualitative Clinical Chemistry".
Biographical note
1883 Born March 29, Pike, New York
1901-1902 Hobart College, Geneva, New York
1905 A.B. University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan
1907 Ph. D. University of Michigan
1907-1908 Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York Fellow in Chemistry with P.A.T. Levene
1908-1911 RIMR Assistant in Chemistry
1911 University of Berlin, studied with Emil Fischer
1912-1914 RIMR Associate Member
1914-1920 RIMR Hospital Associate Member, Chief chemist
1917 Visiting Professor University of California
1920-1948 RIMR Hospital Member
1922-1923 Visiting Professor Peking Medical College
1948-1971 Member Emeritus RIMR
1949-1951 Brookhaven National Laboratory, Asst. Dir. for Research in Biology and Medicine
1951-1971 Brookhaven National Laboratory, Research Chemist
1971 Died May 4, Garden City, New York
Honorary degrees
1925 Sc. D. Yale University
1935 Sc. D. University of Michigan
1938 M.D. University of Oslo
1940 Sc. D. Northwestern University
1941 Sc. D. University of Chicago
1951 Sc. D. University of London
1962 M.D. University of Amsterdam
1966 Sc. D. Rockefeller University
1970 M.D. University of Ulm
Awards
1936 Charles Mickle Fellowship. University of Toronto
1936 Phillip A. Conne Medal. Chemist's Club of New York
1939 Willard Gibbs Medal. Chicago Section American Chemical Society
1939 Order of the Jade Republic of China
1942 Kober Medal. Association of American Physicians
1947 Order of the Brilliant Star. Republic of China
1953 Fisher Award in Analytical Chemistry. American Chemical Society
1954 John Phillips Memorial Award. American College of Physicians
1957 Van Slyke Award in Clinical Chemistry. 1st - American Association of Clinical Chemists
1962 Scientific Achievement Award. 1st - American Medical Association
1964 Ames Award. American Association of Clinical Chemistry
1965 National Medal of Science. U.S.A.
1965 Elliott Cresson Award. Franklin Society of Philadelphia
1966 Medal. New York Academy of Medicine
Served:
1914-1924 Managing Editor Journal of Biological Chemistry
1940-1947 American Bureau for Medical Aid to China/President
1949 First International Congress of Biochemistry, Cambridge, Eng Honorary Vice-President
1951-1956 Counselor Eli Lilly Research Grants
1957 International Congress of Clinical Chemistry, Stockholm Honorary President
1969 Seventh Congress of Clinical Chemistry, Geneva, Switzerland Honorary President
Member of: National Academy of Sciences, American Philosophical Society, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Rudolf Virchow Medical Society in NYC, American College of Cardiology (honorary), American Society of Biological Chemists (President 1920-1922), Harvey Society (President 1927-1928), American Chemical Society, Association of American Physicians, Sigma Xi, Beta Theta Pi, Society of Experimental Biology
Honorary Member of: Soc. Chem. Biol. (Italian), Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher, Societa Lombarda di Medicina, Academy of Science of India, Society of Biological Chemists of India, Royal Society of Sciences of Uppsala, Danish Society for Internal Medicine, Société de Pathologie Rénale, Società Italiana di Biologia Sperimentale, Association of Clinical Biochemists (Britain), Accademia Nazionale dei Lincei (Italian), Danish Academy
Custodial History note
Boxes 2, 3, 4 (legal size Hollinger) and oversize packages 1, 2, 3, 4 originate from the Else Van Slyke collection. Box 5 and 6 originate from the Keller Van Slyke collection.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 V364
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Bibliography
PapersVan Slyke, D.D. and Van Slyke, L.L. The action of dilute acids upon casein when no soluble compounds are formed. NY Agr Exper Sta 3: 79 (1906); Amer Chem J 38: 383 (1907).
Gomberg, M. and Van Slyke, D.D. The action of molecular silver, of silver sulfate and chloride, and of sulfuric acid upon halogenated derivatives of triphenylcarbinolchloride. J Amer Chem Soc 33: 531 (1907).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Van Slyke, L.L. Absorption of acids by casein. J Biol Chem 4: 259 ' (1908).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Zür Methodik der Destination der Amino-aaurenester mittles der Geryk-Pumpe. Biochem Z 10: 214 (1908).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Hydrolyse von Wittepepton. Biochem Z 13: 440 (1908).Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Ueber Plastein. Biochem Z 13: 458 (1908).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Ueber Plastein. II. Biochem Z 14: 203 (1909).
Van Slyke, D.D. Clavin, Vahlen's active constituent of ergot. J Pharmacol Exp Ther 1: 265 (1909).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. The leucin fraction of proteins. J Biol Chem 6: 391 (1909).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. The leucin fraction in casein and edestin. J Biol Chem 6: 419 (1909).
Levene, P.A., Van Slyke, D.D. and Birchard, P.J. The partial hydrolysis of proteins. II. On Fibrin-heteroalbumose. J Biol Chem 8: 269 (1910).
Van Slyke, D.D. Eine Methode zür quantitativen Bestimmung der alipha-tischen Aminogruppen; einige Anwenungen derselben in der Chemi der Proteine, des Harns und der Enzyme. Ber d Deutsch Chem Gesellsch 43: 3170 (1910).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Note on insoluble lead salts of amino acids. J Biol Chem 8: 285 (1910).
Fischer, E. and Van Slyke, D.D. Ueber einige Verwandlung der - Pyrrol-carbonsaure. Ber Deutsch Chem Gesellsch 44: 3166 (1911).
Van Slyke, D.D. A method for quantitative determination of aliphatic amino groups. Applications to the study of proteolysis and proteolytic products. J Biol Chem 9: 185 (1911).
Van Slyke, D.D. The analysis of proteins by determination of the chemical groups characteristic of the different amino acids. J Biol Chem 10: 15 (1911).
Abderhalden, E. and Van Slyke, D.D. Die Bestimmung des Aminostickstoffs in einigen Polypeptiden nach der Methode von Van Slyke.
Zeits f Physiol Chem 74: 505 (1911).Van Slyke, D.D. and White, G.F. Digestion of protein In the stomach and intestine of the dogfish. J Biol Chem 9: 209 (1911).
Van Slyke, D.D. and White, G.F. The relation between the digestibility and the retention of ingested proteins. J Biol Chem 9: 219 (1911).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Picrolonates of the monoamino acids. J Biol Chem 12: 127 (1912).Van Slyke, D.D. The quantitative determination of aliphatic amino broups. II. J Biol Chem 12: 275 (1912).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Gasometric determination of free and conjugated amino acids in the urine. J Biol Chem 12: 301 (1912).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. The composition and properties of glycocoll picrate and the separation of glycocoll from alanine. J Biol Chem 12: 285 (1912).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Meyer, G.M. The amino-acid nitrogen of the blood. Preliminary experiments on protein assimilation. J Biol Chem 12: 399 (1912).
Van Slyke, D.D. The gasometric determination of aliphatic amino nitrogen in minute quantities. J Biol Chem 16: 121 (1913).
Levene, P.A. and Van Slyke, D.D. The separation of d-alanine and à-valine. J Biol Chem 16: 103 (1913).
Van Slyke, D.D. Improved methods in the gasometric determination of free and conjugated amino-acid nitrogen in the urine. J Biol Chem 16: 125 (1913).
Van Slyke, D.D. The fate of protein digestion products in the body. II. Determination of amino nitrogen in the tissues. J Biol Chem 16: 187 (1913).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Meyer, G.M. The fate of protein digestion products in the body. III. The absorption of amino acids from the blood by the tissues. J Biol Chem 16: 197 (1913).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Meyer, G.M. The fate of protein digestion products in the body. IV. The locus of chemical transformation of absorbed amino acids. J Biol Chem 16: 213 (1913).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Meyer, G.M. The fate of protein digestion products in the body. V. The effects of feeding and fasting on the amino-acid content of the tissues. J Biol Chem 16: 231 (1913).
Auer, J. and Van Slyke, D.D. A contribution to the relation between protein cleavage products and anaphylaxis. J Exp Med 18: 210 (1913).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Cullen, G.E. The mode of action of urease and of enzymes in general. J Biol Chem 19: 141 (1914).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Zacharias, G. The effect of hydrogen-ion concentration and of inhibiting substances on urease. J Biol Chem 19: 181 (1914).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Cullen, G.E. A permanent preparation of urease and its use in the determination of urea. J Biol Chem 19: 211 (1914).
Bilis, A., Cullen, G. and Van Slyke, D.D. The amino acid content of the blood and spinal fluid of syphilitic and nonsyphilitic individuals. JAMA 64: 126 (1915).
McLean, F.C. and Van Slyke, D.D. A method for the determination of chlorides in small amounts of body fluids. J Biol Chem 21: 361 (1915).
McLean, F.C. and Van Slyke, D.D. A method for the titration of small amounts of halides. J Amer Chem Soc 37: 1128 (1915).
Van Slyke, D.D., Courtney, A.M. and Fales, H.L. Forms of nitrogen in the stools of infants. Amer J Pis Child 9: 533 (1915).
Levin, T. and Van Slyke, D.D. Results of applying a quantitative method to the Abderhalden serum test for cancer. JAMA 65: 945 (1915).
Van Slyke, D.D. Improvements in the method for analysis of proteins by determination of the chemical groups characteristic of the different amino acids. J Biol Chem 22: 281 (1915).
Osborne, T.B., Van Slyke, D.D., Leavenworth, D.S. and Vinograd, M. Some products of the hydrolysis of gliadin, lact-albumin, and the protein of the rice kernel. J Biol Chem 22: 259 (1915).
Van Slyke, D.D. Analysis of proteins by determination of the chemical group characteristic of the different amino acids.. J Biol Chem 23: 411 (1915).
Van Slyke, D.D., Vinograd-Villchur, M. and Losee, J.R. The Abderhalden reaction. J Biol Chem 23: 377 (1915).
Van Slyke, D.D. Note on the micro method for gasometric determination of aliphatic amino nitrogen. J Biol Chem 23: 407 (1915).
Van Slyke, D.D., Stillman, E. and Cullen, G.E. The nature and detection of diabetic acidosis. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 12: 165 (1915).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Cullen, G.E. The determination of urea by the urease method. J Biol Chem 24: 117 (1916).
Van Slyke, D.D., Losee, J.R. and Vinograd-Villchur, M. A quantitative test of the Abderhalden reaction. Amer J Obs Dis Women Child 63: 1 (1916).
Van Slyke, D.D. The present significance of the amino acids in physiology and pathology. Arch Intern Med 19: 56 (1917).
Van Slyke, D.D. The determination of oxygen in blood. Proc Soc Exp Med 14: 84 (1917).
Losee, J.R. and Van Slyke, D.D. The toxemias of pregnancy. Amer J Med Sci 153: 94 (1917).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Cullen, G.E. The mode of action of urease and of enzymes in general. J Biol Chem 28: 391 (1917).
Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of lung volume. Trans Ass Amer Phys Surg 32: 404 (1917).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Cullen, G.E. Studies of acidosis. I. The bicarbonate concentration of the blood plasma; its significance and its determination as a measure of acidosis. J Biol Chem 30: 289 (1917).
Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. II. A method for the determination of carbon dioxide and carbonates in solution. J Biol Chem 30: 347 (1917).
Cullen, G.E. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. III. The electrometric titration of plasma as a measure of its alkaline reserve. J Biol Chem 30: 369 (1917).
Fitz, R. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. IV. The relationship between alkaline reserve and acid excretion. J Biol Chem 30: 389 (1917).
Van Slyke, D.D., Stillman, E. and Cullen, G.E. Studies of acidosis. V. Alveolar carbon dioxide and plasma bicarbonate in normal men during digestive rest and activity. J Biol Chem 30: 401 (1917).
Stillman, E., Van Slyke, D.D., Cullen, G.E. and Fitz, R. Studies of acidosis. VI. The blood, urine, and alveolar air in diabetic acidosis. J Biol Chem 30: 405 (1917).
Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. VII. The determination of β-hydroxybutyric acid, acetoacetic acid, and acetone in urine. J Biol Chem 32: 455 (1917).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Fitz, R. Studies of acidosis. VIII. The determination of β-hydroxybutyric acid, acetoacetic acid, and acetone in blood. J Biol Chem 32: 495 (1917).
Palmer, W.W. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. IX. Relationship between alkali retention and alkali reserve in normal and pathological individuals. J Biol Chem 32: 499 (1917).
Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of lung volume. I. Relation between thorax size and lung volume in normal adults. J Exp Med 27: 65 (1918).
Garvin, A., Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of lung volume. II. Tuberculous men. J Exp Med 27: 87 (1918).
Garvin, A., Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of lung volume III. Tuberculous women. J Exp Med 27: 129 (1918).
Van Slyke, D.D. Gasometric determination of the oxygen and hemoglobin of blood. J Biol Chem 33: 127 (1918).
Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. X. J Biol Chem 33: 271 (1918).
Whipple, G.H. and Van Slyke, D.D. Proteose intoxications and injury of body protein. J Exp Med 28: 213 (1918).
Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. XI. The determination of carbon dioxide in carbonates. J Biol Chem 36: 351 (1918).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Palmer, W. Titration of organic acid in urine. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 16: 140 (1919).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Stillman, E. Excretion of urea. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 17: 59 (1919).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Donleavy, J. A simplification of the McLean-Van Slyke method for determination of plasma chlorides. J Biol Chem 37: 551 (1919).
Van Slyke, D.D., Stillman, E. and Cullen, G.E. Studies of acidosis. XIII. A method for titrating the bicarbonate content of the plasma. J Biol Chem 38: 167 (1919).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Fitz, R. The determination of β-hydroxybutyric acid, acetoacetic acid, and acetone in blood. J Biol Chem 39: 23 (1919).
Hiller, A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Direct determination of non-amino nitrogen in the products of protein hydrolysis. J Biol Chem 39: 470 (1919).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Salvesen, H.A. The determination of carbon monoxide in blood. J Biol Chem 40: 103 (1919).
Stadie, W.C. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. XV. Carbon dioxide. content and capacity in arterial and venous blood plasma. J Biol Chem 41: 191 (1920).
Van Slyke, D.D. Chemistry of proteins. Chap. V Oxford System of Medicine 1: 251 (1920).
Austin, J.E. and Van Slyke, D.D. Determination of chlorides in whole blood. J Biol Chem 41: 345 (1920).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Palmer, W.W. Studies of acidosis. XVI. The titration of organic acids in urine. J Biol Chem 41: 567 (1920).
Cullen, G.E. and Van Slyke, D.D. Determination of the fibrin, globulin, and albumin nitrogen of blood plasma. J Biol Chem 41: 587 (1920).
Stadie, W.C. and Van Slyke, D.D. The effect of acute yellow atrophy on metabolism and on the composition of the liver. Arch Intern Med 25: 693 (1920).
Van Slyke, D.D. The carbon dioxide carriers of the blood. Physiol Rev 1: 141 (1921).
Austin, J.H. and Van Slyke, D.D. The determination of chlorides in blood plasma. J Biol Chem 45: 461 (1921).
Austin, J.H., Stillman, E. and Van Slyke, D.D. Factors governing the excretion rate of urea. J Biol Chem 46: 91 (1921).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Binger, C.A.L. The determination of lung volume without forced breathing. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 18: 141 (1921).
Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. XVII. The normal and abnormal variations in the acid-base balance of the blood. J Biol Chem 48: 153 (1921).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Stadie, W.C. The determination of the gases of the blood. J Biol Chem 49: 1 (1921).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Hiller, A. An unidentified base among the hydrolytic products of gelatin. Proc Nat Acad Sci USA 7: 185 (1921).
Van Slyke, D.D. An apparatus for determination of the gases in blood and other solutions. Proc Nat Acad Sci USA 7: 299 (1921).
Van Slyke, D.D. Die Analyse von Eiweisskörpern durch Bestimmung der chemisch charakteristischen Grüppen der verschiedenen Aminosäuren. Abderhalden's Hand d biol Arbeit Abt I Teil 7 53 (1922).
Van Slyke, D.D. Die gasometrische Bestimmung von primarem aliphatischen Aminostickstoff und ihre Andewendung auf physiologischchemischen Gebeiete. Abderhalden's Hand d biol Arbeit Abt I Teil 7 263 (1922).
Van Slyke, D.D. On the measurement of buffer values and on the relationship of buffer value to the dissociation constant of the buffer and the concentration and reaction of the buffer solution. J Biol Chem 52: 525 (1922).
Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of acidosis. XVIII. Determination of the bicarbonate concentration of the blood and plasma. J Biol Chem 52: 495 (1922).
Hiller, A. and Van Slyke, D.D. A study of certain protein precipitants. J Biol Chem 53: 253 (1922).
Hastings, A.B. and Van Slyke, D.D. The determination of the three dissociation constants of citric acid. J Biol Chem 53: 269 (1922).
Van Slyke, D.D., Austin, J.H. and Cullen, G.E. The effect of ether anesthesia on the acid-base balance of the blood. J Biol Chem 53: 277 (1922).
Austin, J.E., Cullen, G.E., Hastings, A.B., McLean, F.C., Peters, J.P. and Van Slyke, D.D. J Biol Chem 54: 121 (1922). Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. The quantitative influences of certain factors involved in the production of cyanosis. Proc Nat Acad Sci USA 8: 280 (1922).
Van Slyke, D.D., Hastings, A.B., Heidelberger, M. and Neill, J.M. Studies of gas and electrolyte equilibria in blood. III. The alkali-binding and buffer values of oxyhemoglobin and reduced hemoglobin. J Biol Chem 54: 481 (1922).
Van Slyke, D.D., Hastings, A.B. and Neill, J.M. Studies of gas and electrolyte equilibria in blood. IV. The effect of oxygenation and reduction on the bicarbonate content and buffer value of blood. J Biol Chem 54: 507 (1922).
Van Slyke, D.D. Acidosin. Endocrinology and Metabolism 4: 51-93. L.F. Barker, Ed. Appleton, 1922.Van Slyke, D.D. and Binger, C.A.L. The determination of lung volume without forced breathing. J Exp Med 37: 457 (1923).
Linder, G.C., Lundsgaard, C., Van Slyke, D.D. and Stillman, E. The cause of low plasma protein concentration in nephritis. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 20: 319 (1923).
Linder, G.C., Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. The globulin and albumin content of the plasma in nephritis. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 20: 320 (1923).
Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. Cyanosis. Medicine 2: 1 (1923).
Van Slyke, D.D., Wu, H. and McLean, F.C. Studies of gas and electrolyte equilibria in the blood. V. Factors controlling the electrolyte and water distribution in the blood. J Biol Chem 56: 765 (1923).
Van Slyke, D.D. The determination of chlorides in blood and tissues. J Biol Chem 58: 523 (1923).
Linder, G. C., Lundsgaard, C., Van Slyke, D.D. and Stillman, E. Changes in the volume of plasma and absolute amount of plasma proteins in nephritis. J Exp Med 39: 921 (1924).
Linder, G.C., Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. The concentration of the plasma proteins in nephritis. J Exp Med 39: 887 (1924).
Hiller, A., Linder, G.C., Lundsgaard, C. and Van Slyke, D.D. Fat metabolism in nephritis. J Exp Med 39: 931 (1924).
Hastings, A.B., Van Slyke, D.D., Neill, J.M., Heidelberger, M. and Harrington, C.R. Studies of gas and electrolyte equilibria in blood. VI. The acid properties of reduced and oxygenated hemoglobin. J Biol Chem 60: 89 (1924).
Van Slyke, D.D., Hastings, A.B., Murray, CD. and Davies, H.W. Blood reaction and respiration. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 22: 82 (1924).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Neill, J.M. The determination of gases in blood and other solutions by vacuum extraction and manometric measurement. I. J Biol Chem 61: 523 (1924).
Harrington, C.R. and Van Slyke, D.D. On the determination of gases in blood and other solutions by vacuum extraction and manometric measurement. II. J Biol Chem 61: 575 (1924).
Linder, G.C., Hiller, A. and Van Slyke, D.D. Carbohydrate metabolism in nephritis. J Clin Invest 1: 247 (1925).
Van Slyke, D.D. Gasometric determination of urea with urease. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 22: 486 (1925).
Hiller, A., Linder, G.C. and Van Slyke, D.D. The reducing substances of the blood. J Biol Chem 64: 625 (1925).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Robson, W. Unknown product hydrolysis of gelatin. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 23: 23 (1925).
Van Slyke, D.D., Hastings, A.B., Murray, CD. and Sendroy, J., Jr. Studies of gas and electrolyte equilibria in blood. VIII. The distribution of hydrogen, chloride, and bicarbonate ions In oxygenated and reduced blood. J Biol Chem 65: 701 (1925).
Van Slyke, D.D. The determination of gases in blood and other solutions by vacuum extraction and manometric measurement. III. Gasometric determination of methemoglobin. J Biol Chem 66: 409 (1925).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Vollmund, E. Studies of methemoglobin formation. J Biol Chem 66: 415 (1925).
Van Slyke, D.D., Linder, G.C., Miller, A., Leiter, L. and Mcintosh, J.P. The excretion of ammonia and titratable acid in nephritis. J Clin Invest 2: 235 (1926).
Van Slyke, D.D. Bostimmung der Alkalireserve des Blutes. Abdarhalden Handbuch der biologischen Arbeitsmethoden Abt. IV Teil 4 1245 (1926).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Hiller, A. The residual reduction of blood. J Biol Chem 68: 323 (1926).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Hawkins, J.A. Gasometric determination of blood sugar. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 24: 168 (1926).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Sendroy, J., Jr. Gasometric determination of blood calcium. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 24: 167 (1926).
Van Slyke, D.D. Gasometric micro-Kjeïdahl determination of nitrogen. J Biol Chem 71: 235 (1927).
Van Slyke, D.D. La Formule Ureo-Secretoire D'Ambard et les resultats de Austin, Stillman et Van Slyke. La Presse Medicale 35: 214 (1927).
Hastings, A.B., Salvesen, H.A., Sendroy, J., Jr. and Van Slyke, D.D. Studies of gas and electrolyte equilibria in the blood. IX. The distribution of electrolytes between transudates and serum. J Gen Physiol 8: 701 (1927).
Van Slyke, D.D. and Robscheit-Robbins, F.S. The gasometric determination of small amounts of carbon monoxide in blood, and its application to blood volume studies. J Biol Chem 72: 39 (1927).
Medical research; Medical sciences; Pathology; Enzymes; Enzymology; Life sciences; Physiology; Proteins; Biochemistry; Chemistry; Diseases; Medicine, Preventive; Biology -- Research; Rockefeller University; Van Slyke, Donald D. (Donald Dexter); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Biographical material, photographs, bibliography, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes a short biography written in 1952 at the request of U.S. Gasser for purposes of Institute history.
  - Photographs of co-workers and wife and children
  - Hastings, A. Baird. "Donald Dexter Van Slyke; the 20th Century Iatro-chemist" Proceedings Fed. Am. Soc. Exptl. Biol. 23 (1964) 586-591 in honor of Van Slyke 80th birthday
  - Murphy, Robert Cushman. Funeral Address delivered at Presbyterian Church, Setauket, 1971 May 7
  - Biographical memoir. Yearbook APS. 1971, 194-200, written by Reginald M. Archibald